Guide to the American Board of Commissioners For Foreign Missions Records 1821-1871
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions records
1821-1871
Oregon Historical Society Research Library 1200 SW Park Ave. Portland, OR 97205 libreference@ohs.org https://www.ohs.org/research-and-library/
American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
Mss 1200
0.7 cubic feet 1 legal document case; 1 slim legal document case; 1 shared reel of microfilm
Journal extracts, reports, correspondence, and financial documents of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions (A.B.C.F.M.) concerning its missionary operations in the Oregon Territory. Includes materials relating to discussion by Hawaii missionary Jonathan S. Green and others on the feasibility of having a mission in the Pacific Northwest; and correspondence of missionaries Marcus Whitman, Henry H. Spalding, Cushing Eells, Elkanah Walker, William H. Gray, and A.B.C.F.M. secretaries David Greene and S. B. Treat. Almost all materials are typescript copies, many of them made from originals in the A.F.B.C.M. archives at the Houghton Library of Harvard University.
Collection is open for research.
Acquired prior to 1971, most likely in the early 20th century (RL2021-016-RETRO). Microfilmed materials most likely acquired in 1964 (RL2021-037-RETRO).
The collection is arranged in two series: Series 1. Copies of records from A.B.C.F.M. Archives; Series 2. Other A.B.C.F.M. records.
The American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions was organized in 1810 and was the first missionary society in the United States. Headquartered in Boston, it served as the missionary arm of several major Protestant church denominations, particularly the Congregational, Presbyterian, and Dutch Reformed Churches. The Board established missions all over the world, including the Whitman mission in what would become the Oregon Territory, and later Washington state. The Board was absorbed into the United Church Board of World Ministries in 1961.
Unless otherwise noted, all materials are typescript copies.
Originals of most the materials are housed at the Houghton Library, Harvard University, American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions Archives, ABC 1-91. Original of January 14, 1851, letter from Henry H. Spalding to S. B. Treat is housed in the Whitman College and Northwest Archives, Walla Walla, Washington. Originals of microfilmed materials are held in the Hawaiian Mission Children's Society Library, Honolulu, Hawaii.
Additional papers relating to missionaries in the Pacific Northwest are designated Mss 1201 through Mss 1225, and Microfilm Mss 1200-1225, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
The bulk of the collection consists of typescript copies of journal extracts, reports, correspondence, and financial documents of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions concerning its missionary operations in the Oregon Territory. Many of the typescripts are based on originals held in the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions archives in the Houghton Library at Harvard University, and are referred to by the sequential numbers that the Houghton Library assigned. The collection includes the reports of Jonathan S. Green (a missionary based in Hawaii) on his exploration of the northwest coast of North America, and correspondence and records relating to discussions on whether establishing a mission in the Pacific Northwest would be worthwhile. Missionaries to the Pacific Northwest who are represented in this collection are William H. Gray, Henry H. Spalding, Cushing Eells, Elkanah Walker, and Marcus Whitman, as well as Board secretary David Greene. There are a few original items and photostatic copies of documents in the collection in addition to the typescripts.
Spalding, Henry Harmon, 1803-1874; Greene, David, active 1838-1847; Whitman, Marcus, 1802-1847; Gray, W. H. (William Henry), 1810-1889; Eells, Cushing, 1810-1893; Walker, Elkanah, 1805-1877; Green, Jonathan S. (Jonathan Smith), 1796-1878
American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
Indians of North America--Missions--Northwest, Pacific; Missionaries--Northwest, Pacific
Missionaries
correspondence; typescripts
- Copies of records from A.B.C.F.M. Archives, 1828-1859; Series 1
  - Archives of the A.B.C.F.M., Volume 71, 1835-1836; Subseries 1
    - Letters 196-204: Henry H. Spalding to David Greene; journal of Henry H. Spalding, 1835-1836; 1836 September 21-October 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Archives of the A.B.C.F.M., Volume 137, 1839-1840; Subseries 2
    - Letters 121-125: E. O. Hall to R. Anderson and Henry H. Spalding, 1839-1840 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Archives of the A.B.C.F.M., Volume 138, 1837-1844; Subseries 3
    - Index, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters 1-20: Various correspondents, including Henry H. Spalding, Marcus Whitman, William H. Gray, and Elkanah Walker, 1837-1843 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters 21-30: Henry H. Spalding to David Greene, 1837-1839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters 31-40: Henry H. Spalding to David Greene, 1838-1843 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters 41-47: Cushing Eells to David Greene, 1840-1844 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters 48-60: Asa Bowen Smith to David Greene, 1838-1840 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letter 61: Asa Bowen Smith to H. Bingham, 1840 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters 62-70: Asa Bowen Smith to David Greene, 1840-1842 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters 71-82: Elkanah Walker to David Greene, 1838-1844 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters 83-90: Marcus Whitman to David Greene, 1837-1840 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters 91-107: Marcus Whitman to David Greene, 1840-1844 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters 108-120: William H. Gray to David Greene, 1837-1838 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters 121-135: William H. Gray to David Greene, 1838-1842 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters 136-141: William H. Gray to various correspondents including John McLoughlin; report of William H. Gray, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letters 142-146: Cornelius Rogers to David Greene, 1839-1841 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter 147: P. B. Littlejohn to David Greene; fragment of letter pasted to end of Volume 138, 1843 March 31; undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Archives of the A.B.C.F.M., Volume 248, 1828-1859; Subseries 4
    - Index to Letters 76-139 and 159-175, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letter 76: Memorandum of letter from General William H. Ashley to Edward Bates dated February 20, 1828, written by Jeremiah Evarts, 1828 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letter 77: List of distance between Independence, Missouri, and Walla Walla, Oregon Territory, circa 1843 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letter 78: Report of Marcus Whitman submitted to the Prudential Committee, 1843 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letters 79-81: Inventories of A.B.C.F.M. material goods lost or destroyed in the Whitman killings, and related affidavits, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letter 82: Statement of expenses of the Oregon mission, circa 1851 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Titles of letters 83 and 84 (text of letters was not copied), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Letters 85-91: Various correspondence, including by Amory Holbrook, George H. Atkinson, and Benjamin Alvord, 1850-1854 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Letter 92: Correspondence from Andrew Rogers and Henry H. Spalding to David Greene, 1847 October 13-14 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Letters 93-95: Correspondence from Cushing Eells, Henry H. Spalding, and Elkanah Walker to S. B. Treat, 1851 October 22-December 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Letters 96-107: Cushing Eells to David Greene, 1847-1848 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Letter 108: Letter from John Lee Lewes, chief factor of Hudson's Bay Company, commending Cushing Eells, 1848 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Letters 109-127: Cushing Eells to S. B. Treat, 1849-1859 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Letter 128: William H. Gray to David Greene (2 copies), 1843 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Letters 129-133: Henry H. Spalding to David Greene, 1843-1846 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Letters 134-139: Henry H. Spalding to David Greene, 1847-1859 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letter 159: Elkanah Walker to William G. Armstrong and David Greene, 1844 April 20; 1845 October 8 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters 160-166: Elkanah Walker to David Greene; extract of letter from Mary Richardson Walker to "Mrs. Hill", 1845-1848 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters 167-175: Elkanah Walker to S. B. Treat, 1851-1859 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Other A.B.C.F.M. records, 1821-1871; Series 2
  - Agreement for Jonathan S. Green's passage aboard the bark Volunteer to the Pacific Northwest (microfilm of original), 1829 February; Mss 1200-Mss 1225 Microfilm (Reel 1)
  - Letters from Jonathan S. Green to Levi Chamberlain and William Richards during Green's expedition in the Pacific Northwest (microfilm of originals), 1829 August 4-11; Mss 1200-Mss 1225 Microfilm (Reel 1)
  - Letters from Jonathan S. Green to the Board about the feasibility of establishing a mission in the Pacific Northwest, 1828-1829 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Extracts from the "Missionary Herald," including pieces about Jonathan S. Green's exploration of the Pacific Northwest coast, 1821-1831 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Report of the Sandwich Island Mission Standing Committee on Oregon Mission, 1830 January 20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Printed volume, "Extracts from the Records of the Hawaiian Association from 1823 to 1836," listing Jonathan S. Green's name (original), 1837 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Samuel Northrup Castle from missionaries in the Oregon Territory, including from William H. Gray, Henry H. Spalding, and George Atkinson (microfilm of originals), 1839-1851; Mss 1200-Mss 1225 Microfilm (Reel 1)
  - Letter from William H. Gray to David Greene (photostatic reproduction), 1838 September 19 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters from David Greene to John Dunbar, Samuel Allis, Jr., and Cyrus Kingsbury, 1834 March 29-September 10 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letter from Henry H. Spalding to the Board, asking to be appointed as missionary, 1835 August 7 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Henry H. Spalding to David Greene, 1835-1836; 1847 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Includes copies of letters that were designated Letters 196-204 in Volume 138 of the A.F.C.B.M. Archives.
  - Letters from Henry H. Spalding to S. B. Treat, 1850-1871 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letter from Henry H. Spalding to the secretaries of the A.B.C.F.M., 1857 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letter from Henry P. Strong to unidentified person, possibly David Greene, 1834 December 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Handbill for A.B.C.F.M. meeting at the Broadway Tabernacle on May 14, 1847 (original) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Instructions of the Prudential Committee to Elkanah Walker, Cushing Eeells, Alvin B. Smith, and William H. Gray (original and two typescript copies), 1838 March 18 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Receipt of expenditures for Henry H. Spalding, Marcus Whitman, and William H. Gray (photostatic reproduction), 1836 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Supply lists, 1841; 1847 (Box 2, Folder 19)